<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The poore orphans court, or Orphans cry. By M.S. Being a wel-wisher for a speedy helpe of their misery, and an eye-witnesse of their present calamitie</title>
            <author>Sparke, Michael, d. 1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12698</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23017.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117720</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852930</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852930</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18285</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12698)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18285)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 585:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The poore orphans court, or Orphans cry. By M.S. Being a wel-wisher for a speedy helpe of their misery, and an eye-witnesse of their present calamitie</title>
                  <author>Sparke, Michael, d. 1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p. : ill. (metal cut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A[nne] G[riffin] for M[ichael] S[parke] junior,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1636.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>M.S. = Michael Sparke.</note>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The orphans court.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 21509 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Orphans --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Social conditions --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:18285:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 80 -->
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Orphans Crye We periſh We Dye</head>
                  <figDesc>depiction of beggars</figDesc>
                  <sp>
                     <q>
                        <l>As Wee you see</l>
                        <l>So may yours Bee</l>
                     </q>
                  </sp>
                  <figure>
                     <sp>
                        <p>for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lords sak<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <sp>
                        <p>For Gods Sake</p>
                     </sp>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <sp>
                        <p>For Criſt Sake</p>
                        <p>O Somm Comfort</p>
                     </sp>
                  </figure>
                  <figure/>
                  <figure/>
                  <figure>
                     <sp>
                        <p>Pitty me in miserye</p>
                     </sp>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <sp>
                        <p>O I am Sick</p>
                     </sp>
                  </figure>
                  <figure/>
                  <figure>
                     <sp>
                        <p>Lay not this Sinn to theyr Charge</p>
                     </sp>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <p>Dead in the Street</p>
                  </figure>
                  <figure/>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18285:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 80 -->
            <p>THE Poore Orphans Court, OR Orphans Cry.</p>
            <p>By M. S.</p>
            <p>Being a wel-wiſher for a ſpeedy helpe of their miſery, and an eye-witneſſe of their preſent calamitie.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. G.</hi> for <hi>M. S.</hi> junior. 1636.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:18285:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 81 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:18285:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 81 -->
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E that ſhal undertake at all times to ſpeake truth in this age (freely from his heart) ſhall be accounted a med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling fellow, not worthy to live in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſociety, but to be ſequeſtred from men. We all know ſome be in feriour, and thoſe men ought not to be ſo little reſpected, as not to be called men, becauſe they have no authority: For there is as well the common Sailer as the Pilot, and hee ſees the ſtorme before it comes, and gives notice to the Pilot how to ſteare his courſe for their beſt ſafegard. So I living this many yeeres, and obſerving this wel-governed Citty, have ſeene as in moſt things ſomething which I thought amiſſe, and might be rectified, which is the great neglect of the poore of this Cittie. I meddle no further, for by my fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent going in all parts earely and late, I have theſe many yeeres obſerved the miſery of the poore but moſt of all of children, young boyes and girles, which for many yeeres I beheld, hoping ever God would open ſome honeſt Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens heart that died rich, that they would doe ſomething to beginne to raiſe a ſtocke. And ſeeing S. <hi>Pauls</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, though not ſufffciently, as alſo Morefields, Alderſgate, Allgate, Newgate, and other good deeds done and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<pb facs="tcp:18285:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 82 -->yet this neglecte<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, I cauſed a Booke to be printed ſome <hi>16.</hi> yeeres agoe, called, Grievons groanes for the Poore. But I being then in the country the booke (whether at the Booke ſellers or at the Printers I know not) loſt the life, and reaſon how the poore ſhould be provided for, by which meanes it loſt all reſpect, and I my good intention; not many yeeres after this, there was a collection for imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the poore, but which way that ſtocke went I have nothing to doe to examine; Not many yeeres after that, that worthy Sir <hi>T. M.</hi> his project came forth, which no doubt had it beene ſeconded, it had taken good effect, for I am perſwaded hee aimed at the generall good of all, but this vaniſhed as a ſhadow; ſince which I have obſerved and finde the laſt remedy is for the children uſed in the weekely Bills, <hi>Dead</hi> in the <hi>Street,</hi> or <hi>ſtarved.</hi> And this is all the remedy I finde for theſe poore ſilly witleſſe creatures. Thoſe that be able to helpe themſelves, I ſpeake not for, but for theſe poore <hi>Orphans,</hi> whoſe Court is kept in a <hi>Cage,</hi> or under a <hi>Stall,</hi> or in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> amongst the formes, the more is the pittie. Wee have an Orphans Court well guided and governed (God be thanked for it) long may it continue, and what trudging and going is there if the rich die and leave wealth to their children, but the poore die and no <hi>Orphans Court</hi> can be found. <hi>Outinam,</hi> thereit is, and not elſe to be found or ſeene. But theſe few lines it may be will be laughed at, I care not though they be; I give my ſelfe content, and wiſh but that may be done here, as is at this preſent in <hi>Dorcheſter, Norwich,</hi> not one ſeene to begge: let us learne of them or of the Dutch, as in the Vniverſity of LEYDEN: where <hi>800.</hi> Orphans are daily fed and ſet at worke, and well provided
<pb facs="tcp:18285:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 82 -->for, how doe the Dutch or French pariſhioners in <hi>LONDON;</hi> can they doe ſo, and not wee? It is nothing but our hard hearts; for mee thinkes I heare ſome ſay, I have but <hi>500.</hi> pounds in my eſtate, I would give one to it, nay I am perſwaded there be <hi>500.</hi> of this minde in this Citie, but either cowardize, or feare of being accounted a vaine-glorious perſon makes them deſiſt, nay, mee thinkes I heare ſome <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> ſay, We will keepe all our poore and well ſome may, if all things were looked into; but theſe Orphans with good looking to would keepe themſelves, witneſſe the willingneſſe of ſome, who you ſhall have of the bigger ſort in Fleet-ſteet in the evenings, with linkes ready to earne a penny to light men, nay, in Smithfield ſtanding by day to ſweepe cleane the waies, how ready are many of them? but the weakeſt goe to the wall, as wee ſee by woefull experience, many whoſe <hi>Toes</hi> and <hi>Legges</hi> are ready to rot off, and worſer mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, which make many a man bluſh to ſee that they are no better provided for. It may be I am de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, would I were. I am verily perſwaded, that many ſpend more in the Taverne idlely than they give the poore willingly. Will not many a Lady ſpend ordinarily day by day five ſhillings to ſee an idle play, or five pounds at a Rere Banquet rather tha<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> give five ſhillings, I beleeve five tokens, to help theſe poore miſerable children. If they heare of a new Play, on goes all the beſt clothes, the Coach-horſes muſt be fetched, and that they may hurry from the poore, the Coach-man ſhall have his charge, to drive away when hee commeth amongſt them; and whats the word? Away with theſe <hi>Stinking-beggers,</hi> but
<pb facs="tcp:18285:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 83 -->when they come home, they will call to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to ſee the dogge have his dinner, but the poore ſhall goe ſupperleſſe to bedd under a ſtall, or in a Porch, <hi>dying</hi> with <hi>miſery,</hi> or <hi>ſtarving</hi> with <hi>cold,</hi> and <hi>hunger.</hi> Theſe are reaſons able to draw a man into a ſerious conſideration for a ſpeedie remedy, and I leave them to thoſe in authority, and reſt ever wiſhing, but not obtaining my deſire, that there were a Court for the poore Orphans as well as the rich.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A wel-wiſher of the poore. <hi>M. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18285:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 83 -->
            <head>The Orphans Court.</head>
            <head type="sub">The poore I thus diſtinguiſh into three ſorts:
<list>
                  <item>1 Sturdy Rogues and Whores.</item>
                  <item>2 Blinde and Lame.</item>
                  <item>3 Aged and Young.</item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt I beginne with the ſturdy Rogue and Whore, and here for theſe there be<note n="*" place="margin">23. Eliza. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cap. 7.34. E, c, 1.7. R. 2. c. 5.12. R. 2. c. 7.11. H. 7. c. 2.19. H. 7. c. 12.22. H. 8, c. 12.27. H. 8. c. 25. 1 E. 6. c. 3.3. E. 6. c. 5. E. 6. c. 2.2. &amp; 3. this and many, c. 5, 5. El. c. 3. all which are expired or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed: &amp; 14. El. c. 5.18. El. c. 3.39. El. c. 4. &amp; 1. lac. cap. 7 vet in force.</note> many good lawes enacted, but few put in execution; and for theſe are appointed Marſhals, and Beadels. But when a Marſhalls eyes be not in all places, or his men will ſcarce look to any, then theſe vermine increaſe; and where theſe are ſturdy, that an old creeping Beadel muſt intreat for feare of knockes, then no Conſtable being ſo bold as hee ought, for feare hee be counted a buſie fellow, then they get maſtery and domineere, and I know no remedy for theſe but two, the one a labouring priſon, or houſe of correction the other the Gallowes, and there I thinke it fitteſt to leave them, being people not worth the ſpeaking of.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort I come to, be the blinde and lame, theſe are ſuffered to beg, and good reaſon,<note n="*" place="margin">18 El. c 3 and the other fore quoted na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures inhibit any to beg</note> but there ought to be no begger but if any be priviledged, then well may theſe, but none may be priviledged, <hi>Ergo,</hi> therefore it were more fit for the <hi>blinde,</hi> to be otherwiſe provided for, and for the <hi>lame,</hi> thoſe that have loſt the uſe of their hands to be provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for, thoſe that have loſt their feet, their hands may be made to ſupply that defect, by divers kindes of workes: as <hi>Net</hi>-making, <hi>Saile</hi>-making, and ſuch like for men. The wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men may <hi>Card</hi> and <hi>Spin,</hi> but that is out of faſhion, a <hi>baudy
<pb facs="tcp:18285:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 84 -->Ballade,</hi> or an <hi>idle Song</hi> are theſe idle peoples greateſt paines, where they make many more idle than themſelves, and there I leave theſe idle people, who might be better imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if they were better looked unto.</p>
            <p>The third ſort be thoſe, which of purpoſe this Tract was written for, theſe be thoſe that I deſire you in office, and in whoſe power it lies, to looke with their eyes, and pitty with their hearts theſe poore wretched miſerable wretches, thoſe who have neither father nor mother, no, nor any friends, thoſe that want wit, reaſon, and are not come to underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, thoſe whoſe yeeres ſpeake not diſcretion, nor have wit to helpe themſelves, and thoſe be they that make blood drop from my heart, whileſt my pen cannot expreſſe their miſery, thoſe of whom <hi>Cheapſide ſtalls,</hi> and <hi>doores,</hi> and <hi>porches,</hi> and S. <hi>Bartholmewes benches,</hi> with <hi>Smith field,</hi> and other corners be witneſſes, to their griefes whoſe eyes if they ſtirre abroad doe not ſee theſe poore younglings, <hi>lame, lowſie, ragged,</hi> and almoſt <hi>ſtarved,</hi> whileſt each haire of their heads ſtand ſtaring in the viewers face, as amazed to ſee ſo many not once moved with pitty to care for them.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſwarme in Summer at the Brickhils and Play-houſe doores, which houſes are the Nurſes of many of theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable wretches, theſe being many are caſt off by wicked parents, or being placed out to <hi>apprentize</hi> by the <hi>Pariſh,</hi> or put to Maſters, are caſt off from one to another, ſo if the <hi>Pariſh</hi> never heare of them againe, but be rid of them they are ſafe; and if the <hi>Nunſes</hi> get but a piece of <hi>money,</hi> they are ſafe, and glad they can ſo be rid of them; this might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed by the Maſters of the <hi>Pariſh,</hi> if they would every three moneth have the children brought to a <hi>Veſtry,</hi> to ſee how they were provided for, but becauſe there is no better proviſion for them, I could wiſh there were ſome courſe tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, as theſe few I will propound, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Pariſh</hi> might take ſuch courſe, as to call all the poore children, and take a view and number of all, and as they come to ability, to ſet out, as namely, by theſe, or ſuch like meanes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18285:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 84 -->
Every Ship being of burden 200. Tuns, ſhould employ two or three boyes.</p>
            <p>Every Coale-ſhip trading to <hi>London</hi> from <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> to take one.</p>
            <p>Every <hi>Pariſh</hi> might raiſe out of the <hi>Pariſh</hi> a ſtocke ſo to employ them, untill they grow to ſome ſtature, then to be ſent to the <hi>Plantations,</hi> to ſome carefull <hi>Maſter</hi> there, and they to give a true account of the children, how, and in what eſtate they be with them.</p>
            <p>Every ſhip that goes to Virginia to carry ſixe <hi>boyes</hi> and ſixe girles, every one to carry the like to New England, and ſo to our other plantations, and the <hi>Pariſh</hi> to pay their paſſage, and at their arivall there, hee that takes them into cuſtody or ſervice, give bond to pay the charge of their fraught and coſts thither to the <hi>Pariſh</hi> here at twelve moneths end backe, which they would doe with thankes, ſo they might have them but ſixe yeeres <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentize;</hi> now ſome demand, where ſhall money be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſend them away? for that I anſwer, the money at the Inqueſt yeerely, may be better ſo employed then to banquetting, and the great feaſt money may be better <hi>ſpared</hi> this waies than worſe <hi>ſpent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this many more and better, courſes may be taken, which I leave to better judgements, for this I know were there but a <hi>Stocke,</hi> raiſed to tranſport them thither, the <hi>Stocke</hi> would be kept whole by thoſe that take them to be their ſervants, by returne of commodities for them, for our <hi>Lawes</hi> they bee good in this kinde, if they were but well executed: as for example, the 22. of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8.</p>
            <p>22. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 12. and 27. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 25. There were acts made for the reliefe of aged and impotent perſons unable to worke, and for <hi>Collections</hi> to be made for ſuch: which acts preſcribe ſevere puniſhments againſt <hi>vagabonds</hi> and ſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>beggars</hi> able to worke.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 3. There was an Act paſſed for the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment
<pb facs="tcp:18285:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 85 -->of <hi>vagabonds,</hi> and the reliefe of the poore and impotent perſons; whereby it was enacted that <hi>Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> ſhould be made in every <hi>Pariſh,</hi> for the impotent <hi>poore</hi> of that <hi>Pariſh:</hi> that thoſe who were aged and lame ſhould be ſet to ſuch worke as they were able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, every <hi>Towne, Pariſh,</hi> or <hi>village</hi> providing ſuch worke for them in common, as they might be occupied in, or appointing them to ſuch as will finde them worke for <hi>meate</hi> and <hi>drinke.</hi> And by this <hi>Law,</hi> it was provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that all children under yeeres of age, whether <hi>Male</hi> or <hi>Female</hi> that wandred abroad by themſelves, or with their parents, or others, might be ſeized upon, and taken away from their parents, by thoſe who would bring them up in ſome honeſt labour, or occupation, till they came to twenty yeares if Females, and foure and twenty yeeres of age if Males: And by this Act, the <hi>Major</hi> of the <hi>Citty</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and all other <hi>Majors, Bailiffes, Sheriffes, Conſtables,</hi> and other head <hi>Officers</hi> of every <hi>Cittie</hi> and <hi>Towne corporate,</hi> are enjoyned once eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry moneth to make a view and examination of all aged, impotent, and lame perſons and beggars within the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct of their juriſdiction, to ſee thoſe that were lame, and had lyen there above the ſpace of three whole yeeres, ſufficiently provided for, and to ſend all others home to the places where they were borne, &amp;c. upon paine of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting 40. ſhillings for every default.</p>
            <p>See 5. <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 2. and 3. <hi>Phil.</hi> and <hi>Mar. c.</hi> 5.5. <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 3.14. <hi>E. c.</hi> 5.18, <hi>El.c.</hi> 3.39. <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 4.5 5.43. <hi>Eliz. c.</hi> 2.3.4. There were divers good <hi>Lawes</hi> enacted for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of poore, impotent, aged, maimed, and decrepit per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; and good proviſions made for poore <hi>Orphans,</hi> and children too, which are to be bound, and placed out to husbandry, or ſome other honeſt trade and labour; or to be ſet on worke upon a common ſtocke, or be trained up in <hi>Hoſpitalls,</hi> till they are fit to be <hi>apprentizes, &amp;c.</hi> which <hi>Lawes,</hi> if they were as carefully executed, as they were
<pb facs="tcp:18285:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 85 -->piouſly made, no <hi>Orphans,</hi> nor other neede complaine, I am ſure never any ſhould periſh in the ſtreet for want of looking to, which is onely the fault of Officers, not of the Lawes, which are no way defective, either in inflicting ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne puniſhment upon vagrant ſturdy beggers, who refuſe to worke, or in providing for the reliefe of <hi>Orphans,</hi> and poore impotent perſons who are unable to labour.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The <hi>Overſeers</hi> of the <hi>poore</hi> of every <hi>Pariſh</hi> appointed purpoſely by the <hi>Law,</hi> to ſee the <hi>impotent, poore,</hi> and <hi>Orphans</hi> duly relieved, ought every weeke to enquire what poore there are in their pariſhes, and to allot them a competent al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance according to their neceſſities.</item>
               <item>2 Theſe <hi>Overſeers</hi> ſhould weekely enquire how theſe <hi>Orphans</hi> and <hi>impotent perſons,</hi> which they place out to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are provided for, and to examine whether they have food ſufficient allowed them, and in caſe they finde them with whom they are placed, negligent in providing for them, or in ſuffering them to ſtray abroad, and ſo to periſh, or miſcarry, to complaine of them to the Magiſtrates who have power to inflict ſuch puniſhments on them, as the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of their offence demerits.</item>
               <item>3 Thoſe <hi>chidren</hi> that are of age and ſtrength to worke, ought to be bound out to ſome trade or other, or elſe ſet to worke upon ſome common pariſh ſtocke, of which the <hi>Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers</hi> of the poore for the time being, or ſome others deputed by the <hi>Pariſh,</hi> ſhould have the mannaging and government, appointing every <hi>child</hi> to that worke hee is fit, and ſetting ſome Maſter worke-man over them who ſhould inſtruct them.</item>
               <item>4 The <hi>Conſtables, Overſeers</hi> of the poore, and <hi>Beadells,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if they ſee any ſuch poore <hi>Orphans,</hi> or <hi>children,</hi> or other <hi>impotent perſons, begging, playing,</hi> or <hi>loytering</hi> in the ſtreetes, ſhould preſently examine them what they are, and where they live: If in another <hi>Pariſh</hi> they ſhould preſently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey them thither, and acquaint the <hi>Overſeers</hi> of the <hi>poore,</hi> or <hi>Conſtables</hi> with them, that ſo it might keep them &amp; provide
<pb facs="tcp:18285:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 86 -->for them if neede be according as our lawes preſcribe. If their owne pariſh, if they are poore and neede reliefe, they are forthwith to take care for their ſupply and education, and in caſe they are fit for any worke or emploiment, to ſet them to that they are able to performe, and to traine them up or place them out to ſuch who will bring them up to ſome honeſt labour.</item>
               <item>5 When ſuch <hi>Orphans</hi> and <hi>poore children</hi> are thus placed out apprentiſes, the <hi>Overſeers</hi> and ſuch as binde them out ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentiſes, and their ſucceſſors, or at leaſtwiſe the <hi>Overſeers</hi> of the pariſhes, or Maſters, or <hi>Alderman</hi> of the ſeverall ward, where they are placed, ought, and may monethly enquire, how they are uſed by their Maſters, whether they allow them competent food and raiment, while they keepe them to their work, and give them that which is fit for Chriſtians, or perſons of their age and quality: whether they keepe them in their ſervice, or elſe turne them away without juſt cauſe, (in all or ſome of which many Maſters are often delinquent) And in caſe they find them pervert, to complaine againſt them for it, that ſo they may be puniſhed in a juſt and legall manner.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And if all <hi>Overſeers</hi> of the <hi>poore, Conſtales, Beadles</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Officers</hi> would be but thus diligent in their places, or if ſuperiour <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> would but puniſh them ſeverely, as our lawes appoint, where they finde them negligent in their duties, wee ſhould quickely have no begging, no periſhing, nor complaining in our ſtreets.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18285:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 86 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
